<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<section
	id="section-Deploying_and_Undeploying_Resource_Adapters">
	<title>Deploying and Undeploying Resource Adapters</title>
	<section
		id="section-Before_You_Begin_Resource_Adapters_and_Deployable_Unit_Files">
		<title>Before You Begin: Resource Adapters and Deployable Unit Files</title>
		<para>Resource adapters are JAIN SLEE components that can be deployed (i.e. <quote>loaded</quote> or <quote>installed</quote>) into the Mobicents Converged Application Server, and undeployed (<quote>uninsntalled</quote>) from it. At the file level, resource adapters consist of specially-named files called deployable unit files. Two of these deployable unit files must be loaded/installed before the Mobicents Converged Application Server will deploy the resource adapter. The next few sections will teach you how to locate where resource adapters and their files live, and how to deploy them and undeploy them through several different, though equivalent ways: via the command line; by copying the correct files to a special directory, or removing them from it; or with the Mobicents Management Console.</para>
		<para>Which of these various ways of accomplishing the same task is easier depends on you. If you are comfortable with the command line, or like to script behavior, then deploying via the command line will probably be the best way for you. If you would prefer to simply copy or delete some files with the file manager, you can do it that way. And for those who prefer graphical user interfaces (<acronym>GUI</acronym>s), the Management Console provides an interface to the Mobicents Converged Application Server, and can easily be used to accomplish such tasks both locally and remotely. However&mdash;no matter which method you eventually choose, it will be necessary to read the following explanatory paragraphs, on where to find the directories corresponding to the resource adapters you want to install, on how to recognize deployable unit files, and on determining the correct order for installing those files, before reading any or all of the method sections.</para>
		<formalpara
			id="fpara-Where_to_Find_Resource_Adapters_in_the_Mobicents_Installation">
			<title>Where to Find Resource Adapters in the Mobicents Installation</title>
			<para>The files with which to install resource adapters are found in <filename><replaceable>&lt;topmost_mobicents_directory&gt;</replaceable>/resources</filename>.</para>
		</formalpara>
		<formalpara
			id="fpara-section-How_to_Recognize_Deployable_Unit_Files">
			<title>section-How_to_Recognize_Deployable_Unit_Files</title>
			<para>Deployable unit files are <acronym>JAR</acronym> (Java ARchive) files. There are two of them</para>
		</formalpara>
		<formalpara
			id="fpara-Correct_Order_for_Installing_Deployable_Unit_Files">
			<title>Correct Order for Installing Deployable Unit Files</title>
			<para></para>
		</formalpara>
	</section>
	<section
		id="section-Deploying_Resource_Adapters">
		<title>Deploying Resource Adapters</title>
		<para></para>
		<section
			id="section-Deploying_Resource_Adapters_Via_the_Command_Line">
			<title>Deploying Resource Adapters Via the Command Line</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-Deploying_Resource_Adapters_By_Copying_Deployable_Unit_Files">
			<title>Deploying Resource Adapters By Copying Deployable Unit Files</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-Deploying_Resource_Adapters_With_the_Management_Console">
			<title>Deploying Resource Adapters With the Management Console</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section
		id="section-Undeploying_Resource_Adapters">
		<title>Undeploying Resource Adapters</title>
		<para></para>
		<section
			id="section-Undeploying_Resource_Adapters_Via_the_Command_Line">
			<title>Undeploying Resource Adapters Via the Command Line</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-Undeploying_Resource_Adapters_By_Removing_Files">
			<title>Undeploying Resource Adapters By Removing Files</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-Undeploying_Resource_Adapters_With_the_Management_Console">
			<title>Undeploying Resource Adapters With the Management Console</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
	</section>
</section>
