<para>
  Overview
</para>
<para>
  &nbsp;
</para>
<para>
  With continued globalization, many corporations have workgroups
  dispersed around the world. To support workgroup productivity and
  communications companies are considering cost effective and less
  expansive network solutions that combine voice, wireless, data and
  video. These businesses expect the services they select and
  implement to have the high quality of the telephone and other
  services they now use, and they expect them to boost productivity
  and help reduce overall communication costs. To access the desired
  network services requires connections from wireless, wireline
  networks, and the Internet to Public Switched Telephone Network
  (PSTN) with flexible, robust, scalable and cost-effective media
  gateway. These gateways must reduce cost of communication of the
  dispersed workgroups and form the foundation for media services.
</para>
<para>
  &nbsp;
</para>
<section>
  <title><ulink url="javascript:void(0);"></ulink>Media gateways
         bridge multiple technologies. <literallayout></literallayout>Today
         all communication can take place through a computer. Widely
         accessible broadband and Internet Protocol (IP) enable voice, data
         and video. Media gateways provide conversation and switching voice
         media between a network and its access point. Digital Subscriber
         Line (DSL) or cable modem a media gateway converts, compress and
         and packetizes voice data for transfer back and forth across the
         Internet backbone for wireline or wireless phones. Media gateways
         fit between the PSTN and wireless or IP-bbased networks.</title>
  <para>
  </para>
</section>
<section>
  <title><ulink url="javascript:void(0);"></ulink>Why modular media
         gateways for VoIP</title>
  <para>
    Several market demands are pushing companies to converge all of
    their media services using media gateways,with VoIP.Companies are
    expecting this architecture to:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Lower initial costs. Capital investment is less because hardware
        can be used for multiple functions.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Lower development costs.Open system hardware and software standards
        with well defined application mean lower costs, and Application
        Programmable Interfaces (AAPIs) accelerate development.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Handle multiple media types. Companies want VoIP solutions today,
        but need to select solutions that will also handle video in the
        near future.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Lower the costs of deployment and maintenance. Standardized,
        modular systems reduce training costs and maintenance while also
        improving uptime.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Enable faster time-tto-mmarket. Early market entry hits the window
        of opportunity and maximizes revenue.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    What is the Mobicents Media Server
  </para>
  <para>
    <literallayout></literallayout>Mobicents Media Gateway is open
    source aimed to:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Deliver competitive, complete, best-of-breed media gateway
        functionality featuring highest quality.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Meet the demands of converged wireless, wireline, cable broadband
        access and fixed-mobile converged VoIP networks from a single media
        gateway platform
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Increase flexibility with a media gateway that supports wide
        variety of call control protocols and scales down to meet the
        demands of enterprises and small carrier providers.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        React quickly to dynamic market requirements.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    &nbsp;
  </para>
  <para>
    <ulink url="/group/mobicents-public/web/mobicents-media-server">TOC</ulink>
  </para>
  <para>
    <ulink url="/group/mobicents-public/web/mobicents-ms-binary">Next</ulink>
  </para>
</section>

