<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<section
	id="section-MMS_Control_Protocols">
	<title>MMS Control Protocols</title>
	<para>The Mobicents Media Server adopts a call control architecture where the call control <quote>intelligence</quote> is located outside of the Media Server itself, and is handled by external call control elements collectively known as Call State Control Function.The media server assumes that these call control elements, or CSCF,will synchronize with each other to send coherent commands and responses to the media servers under their control. Server Control Protocols is, in essence, an asynchronous master/slave protocol, where the Server Control Modules are expected to execute commands sent by CSCF. Each Server Control Module is implemented as a JSLEE application, and consists of a set of Service Building Blocks (<acronym>SBB</acronym>)s which are in charge to communicate with media server's endpoints via SPI. Such an architecture avoids difficulties with programming concurrency, low-level transaction and state-management details, connection-pooling and other complex APIs.</para>
	<formalpara>
		<title>The MGCP Module</title>
		<para>The MGCP module is included in default binary distribution. The Call Agent uses MGCP to tell the Media Server:</para>
	</formalpara>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>which events should be reported to the Call Agent;</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>how endpoints should be connected; and,</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>what signals should be played on which endpoints.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<formalpara>
		<title>Configuring the MGCP Module</title>
		<para>The default port for MGCP is 2728. The Mobicents Management Console can be used to override the default port. For more information about the Management Console, refer to <ulink
				url="section-Working_with_the_Mobicents_Management_Console"/>.</para>
	</formalpara>
</section>

