<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % RH_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../Common_Content/Entities.ent">
%RH_ENTITIES;
<!ENTITY % RH_TRANS_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../Common_Content/Translatable-Entities.ent">
%RH_TRANS_ENTITIES;
]>

<section id="section-Mobicents_XML_Document_Management_Server" xreflabel="XML Document Management Server (XDMS)">
	<title>Mobicents XML Document Manager Server</title>
	<para>
	</para>
	<section id="section-Introduction_to_the_XML_Document_Management_Server">
		<title>Introduction to the XML Document Manager Server</title>
		<para>
			Mobicents <acronym>XDM</acronym> is a free and open source implementation of the XML Document Management server as defined in <orgname>Open Mobile Alliance</orgname>
			 specifications. This functional element of next-generation IP communications networks is responsible for handling the management of user XML documents stored on the network side, such as presence authorization rules, static presence information, contact and group lists (<acronym>a.k.a.</acronym> resource lists), policy data, and many others.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="section-XDM_Server_Architecture">
		<title>XDM Server Architecture</title>
		<para>
			The XML Document Manager Server runs on top of the Mobicents Converged Application Server and is also dependent upon the XCAP (XML Configuration Access Protocol) and <acronym>SIP</acronym> resource adapters.
		</para>
		<para>
			Architecturally, the XDM Server is essentially an <acronym>XCAP</acronym> server that employs a <acronym>SIP</acronym> interface, which allows the server to learn about document updates.
		</para>
		<para>
			The XDM Server can also use an element named the Aggregation Proxy, which is responsible for user authentication and result-caching on XCAP requests.
		</para>
		<para>
			An XDM Server abstracts the element that stores XML documents as a data source.
		</para>
		<figure id="figure-orig-OPENXDM_Functional_Architecture.jpg">
			<title>The Architecture of the Mobicents XML Document Management Server</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata align="center" fileref="images/orig-OPENXDM_Functional_Architecture.jpg" format="JPG" width="700" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<figure id="figure-orig-OpenXDM_JAINSLEE_Implementation.jpg">
			<title>The JAIN SLEE Architectural Implementation of the XDM Server</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata align="center" fileref="images/orig-OpenXDM_JAINSLEE_Implementation.jpg" format="JPG" width="700" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</section>

</section>


