<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<section
	condition="section-binary-SIP_Servlets_Server-Application_Routing_and_Service_Configuration">
	<title>Application Routing and Service Configuration</title>
	<para>The application router is called by the container&#8212;whether JBoss or Tomcat&#8212;to select a SIP Servlet application to service an initial request. It embodies the logic used to choose which applications to invoke. An application router is required for a container to function, but it is a separate logical entity from the container. The application router is solely responsible for application selection and must not implement application logic. For example, the application router cannot modify a request or send a response.</para>
	<para>For more information about the application router, refer to the following sections of the JSR 289 specification: Application Router Packaging and Deployment, Application Selection Process, and Appendix C.
			</para>
	<para>In order to configure the application router, you should edit the <literal>Service</literal> element in the container's <filename>server.xml</filename> configuration file:</para>
	<example
		condition="example-Configuring_the_Service_Element_in_the_Containers_server.xml">
	<title>Configuring the Service Element in the Container's server.xml</title>
<programlisting
			condition="proglist-Configuring_the_Service_Element_in_the_Containers_server.xml"
			linenumbering="numbered"
			role="XML"><![CDATA[<Service
	name="Sip-Servlets"
	className="org.mobicents.servlet.sip.startup.SipStandardService"
	sipApplicationDispatcherClassName="org.mobicents.servlet.sip.core.SipApplicationDispatcherImpl"
	darConfigurationFileLocation="file:///home/silas/workspaces/mobicents-sip-servlets/sip-servlets-examples/reinvite-demo/reinvite-dar.properties">
]]></programlisting>
</example>
	<para>Provided here is a description of the SIP Service element's attributes:</para>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>className</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>This attribute specifies that the servlet container is a <emphasis>converged</emphasis> (i.e. SIP + HTTP) servlet container. This attribute can also be used to handle load-balancing and failover.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>sipApplicationDispatcherClassName</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>This attribute specifies the class name of the <literal>org.mobicents.servlet.sip.core.SipApplicationDispatcher</literal> implementation to use. The routing algorithm and application selection process is performed in that class.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>darConfigurationFileLocation</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>The default application router file location. This is used by the default application router to determine the application selection logic. Refer to Appendix C of the JSR 289 specification for more details.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</section>

