<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]><!--Note: id attributes have been changed to condition atts because I originally tried to use xpointer to pull this section in, which doesn't work with jdocbook-->
<!-- JBoss Application Server -->
<section
	condition="section-binary-JBoss_Application_Server-Installing_Configuring_and_Running">
	<title>JBoss Application Server: Installing, Configuring and Running</title>
	<para>This section instructs you on how to download and install the JBoss Application Server, version 4.2.2 GA, and set the <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> environment variable. Note that you do not need to install JBoss if you are running one of the Mobicents' servers binary releases. You should only follow the instructions below if you are running one or more of the Mobicents servers from source.</para>
	<formalpara
		condition="formalpara-binary-JBoss_Application_Server-PreInstall_Requirements_and_Prerequisites">
		<title>Pre-Install Requirements and Prerequisites</title>
		<para>For the latest information on hardware requirements, software prerequisites, and supported Operating System-and-JVM combinations, please refer to <ulink
				url="http://www.jboss.com"/>.</para>
	</formalpara>
		<!-- <variablelist
			condition="variablelist-binary-JBoss_Application_Server-Hardware_Requirements">
			<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Sufficient Disk Space</term>
				<listitem>
					<para></para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist> -->
		<!-- <variablelist
			condition="variablelist-binary-JBoss_Application_Server-Software_Prerequisites">
			<title>Software Prerequisites</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term></term>
				<listitem>
					<para></para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist> -->
	<formalpara
		condition="formalpara-binary-JBoss_Application_Server-Downloading">
		<title>Downloading</title>
		<para>You can acquire JBoss Application Server 4.2.2 GA from <ulink
				url="http://www.jboss.org/jbossas/downloads/"/>. Click on the <literal>Download</literal> link for <quote>4.2.2.GA</quote> to initiate the actual download from <literal>Sourceforge.net</literal>.</para>
	</formalpara>
	<formalpara
		condition="formalpara-binary-JBoss_Application_Server-Installing">
		<title>Installing</title>
		<para>Once downloaded, installing JBoss merely consists in unzipping the downloaded zip file, optionally moving it to a location of your choice, and, finally, setting the <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> environment variable. You must set <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> so that when you build one of the Mobicents servers from source, it knows into which directory to install the necessary files.</para>
	</formalpara>
	<procedure>
		<title>Installing JBoss AS 4.2.2 GA on Linux</title>
		<step>
			<para>First, move to the directory to which you downloaded the JBoss binary distribution zip file. For this example, we'll assume you're currently in your home directory, and that you downloaded the zip file to a subdirectory of it, referred to as <filename>&lt;downloads&gt;</filename>.</para>
			<screen>~]# cd &lt;downloads&gt;</screen>
		</step>
		<step>
			<para>Finally, use Java's <command>jar <option>-xvf</option>
				</command> command to extract the contents of the zip file.</para>
			<screen>downloads]$ java -jar "jboss-4.2.2.GA.zip"</screen>
			<para>You should now have a directory named <filename>jboss-4.2.2.GA</filename> located in the same directory as the zip file.</para>
		</step>
		<step>
			<para>Optionally, move the JBoss directory to a location of your choice (and do this&#8212;if you're going to&#8212;<emphasis>before</emphasis> setting the <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> environment variable!).</para>
		</step>
		<step>
			<para>Also optionally, you may want to delete the <filename>jboss-4.2.2.GA.zip</filename> zip file in order to conserve space on your system.</para>
		</step>
	</procedure>
	<procedure>
		<title>Installing JBoss AS 4.2.2 GA on Windows</title>
		<step>
			<para>For this example, we'll assume that you downloaded the binary distribution zip file to the <filename>My Downloads</filename> folder. Using Windows Explorer, move into <filename>My Downloads</filename> and double-click on the <filename>jboss-4.2.2.GA.zip</filename> zip file to initiate the unzip process. You can either unzip the compressed <filename>jboss-4.2.2.GA</filename> folder into <filename>My Downloads</filename>, or to another location of your choice (suggested).</para>
			<stepalternatives>
				<step>
					<para>Alternatively, it is also possible to use Java's <command>jar <option>-xvf</option>
									</command> command to extract the binary distribution files from the zip archive. First, open the Windows Command Prompt and change your directory to <filename>My Downloads</filename> (or whereever you downloaded the JBoss zip file to):</para>
					<screen>C:\Users\Me&gt;cd &quot;My Downloads&quot;</screen>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Finally, use the <command>jar <option>-xvf</option>
						</command> command to extract the <filename>jboss-4.2.2.GA</filename> folder into the current folder:</para>
					<screen>C:\Users\Me\My Downloads&gt;jar -xvf "jboss-4.2.2.GA.zip"</screen>
				</step>
			</stepalternatives>
		</step>
		<step>
			<para>Optionally, move the JBoss directory to a location of your choice (and do this&#8212;if you're going to&#8212;<emphasis>before</emphasis> setting the <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> environment variable!).</para>
		</step>
		<step>
			<para>Also optionally, you may want to delete the <filename>jboss-4.2.2.GA.zip</filename> zip file in order to conserve space on your system.</para>
		</step>
	</procedure>
	<!--<formalpara
		condition="formalpara-binary-JBoss_Application_Server-Running">
		<title>Running</title>
		<para></para>
	</formalpara>-->
	<!-- <formalpara
		condition="formalpara-binary-JBoss_Application_Server-Stopping">
		<title>Stopping</title>
		<para></para>
	</formalpara> -->
	<formalpara
		condition="formalpara-binary-JBoss_Application_Server-Configuring">
		<title>Configuring</title>
		<para>Finally, and before continuing with the installatino of one of the Mobicents servers from source, you must set the <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> environment variable. As mentioned, you must set this variable so that when you build one of the Mobicents servers from source, the build system knows where to install the necessary files.</para>
	</formalpara>
	<procedure>
		<title>Setting the <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> Environment Variable on Linux</title>
		<step>
			<para>The <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> environment variable must point to the location of your JBoss AS install, i.e. the topmost directory (<filename>jboss-4.2.2.GA</filename>), the one of which <filename>bin</filename> is a subdirectory.</para>
			<para>Setting this variable in your personal <filename>~/.bashrc</filename> file has the advantage that it will always be set (for you, as a user) each time you log in or reboot the system. To do so, open <filename>~/.bashrc</filename> in a text editor (or create the file if it doesn't already exist) and insert the following line anywhere in the file:</para>
			<screen>export JBOSS_HOME=&quot;/home/&lt;username&gt;/&lt;path&gt;/&lt;to&gt;/jboss-4.2.2.GA&quot;</screen>
			<para>Save and close <filename>.bashrc</filename>.</para>
		</step>
		<step>
			<para>You can&#8212;and should&#8212;<command>source</command> your <filename>.bashrc</filename> file to make your change take effect for the current session:</para>
			<screen>~]$ source ~/.bashrc</screen>
			<important>
				<title>
					<envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> Must Be Set and Correct Before Building Any Server!</title>
				<para>Before you build any Mobicents server using Maven, make sure you <command>echo</command>
					<envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> to make sure it points to the correct location! To be on the absolutely-safe side, you should <command>cd <option>$JBOSS_HOME</option>
					</command> and then <command>pwd</command> to make sure that you end up in the correct directory. Building a Mobicents server with an incorrect <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> value will lead only to confusion and grief!</para>
			</important>
			<screen>~]$ echo $JBOSS_HOME
/home/silas/apps/jboss/jboss-4.2.2.GA
~]$ cd $JBOSS_HOME
jboss-4.2.2.GA]$ pwd
/home/silas/apps/jboss/jboss-4.2.2.GA</screen>
			<para>All good!</para>
		</step>
	</procedure>
	<!-- <formalpara
		condition="formalpara-binary-JBoss_Application_Server-Testing">
		<title>Testing</title>
		<para></para>
	</formalpara> -->
	<formalpara
		condition="formalpara-binary-JBoss_Application_Server-Uninstalling">
		<title>Uninstalling</title>
		<para>To uninstall the JBoss Application Server, simply delete the <filename>jboss-4.2.2.GA</filename> directory.</para>
	</formalpara>
</section>
