<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter
	id="chapter-Installation_of_the_Mobicents_Converged_Application_Server">
	<title>Installation of the Mobicents Converged Application Server</title>
	<para>The Mobicents Converged Application Server can be installed by downloading the ready-to-go binary distribution, or, alterately, the source code can be obtained using the Subversion version control system (<acronym>VCS</acronym>) and then built from source. Installing the binary distribution is recommended for most users, and obtaining and building the source code distribution is recommended for those who want access to the latest revisions and capabilities.</para>
	<section
		id="section-binary-Mobicents-Installing_Configuring_and_Running">
		<title>Binary Distribution: Installing, Configuring and Running</title>
		<para>The Mobicents Converged Application Server runs on top of the JBoss Application Server. The Mobicents 1.20 binary distribution comes bundled with the JBoss Application Server version 4.2.2 GA.</para>
		<section
			id="section-binary-Mobicents-Pre-Install_Requirements_and_Prerequisites">
			<title>Pre-Install Requirements and Prerequisites</title>
			<para>You should ensure a few requirements have been met before continuing with the install.</para>
			<variablelist
				id="variablelist-binary-Mobicents-Hardware_Requirements">
				<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Sufficient Disk Space</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>You must have sufficient disk space in order to install the Mobicents binary release. Once unzipped, version 1.20 (<literal>BETA3</literal>) of the Mobicents binary release requires about 150 MB of free disk space. Keep in mind that disk space requirements may change from release to release.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Anything Java Itself Will Run On</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Both the Mobicents Converged Application Server and the JBoss Application Server are 100% Java. Mobicents will run on the same hardware that the JBoss Application Server runs on.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			<variablelist
				id="variablelist-binary-Mobicents-Software_Prerequisites">
				<title>Software Prerequisites</title>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Java 5 or Higher</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>A working installation of the Java Development Kit (<acronym>JDK</acronym>) version 5 or higher is required in order to run the Mobicents Converged Application Server. Note that the JBoss Application Server is a runtime dependency of Mobicents and, as mentioned, comes bundled with the binary distribution.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-binary-Mobicents-Downloading">
			<title>Downloading</title>
			<para>Download the latest version of the Mobicents binary distribution and, preferably, validate it.</para>
			<procedure
				id="procedure-Downloading_and_Verifying_the_Mobicents_Binary_Distribution">
				<step>
					<para>The latest version of the binary distribution can be found by going to the <ulink
							url="https://sourceforge.net/projects/mobicents/">Mobicents project page on SourceForge.net</ulink>, clicking on <emphasis>Download Mobicents</emphasis>, and then looking for <emphasis>Mobicents Server</emphasis> and <emphasis>Latest Version</emphasis>. This document is written using version the Mobicents binary version 1.20 BETA3.</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Verify the integrity of the zip file. Along with the zip file there is a sha1 file<footnote><para>For the Mobicents 1.20 (<literal>BETA3</literal>) binary release, the relevant file names are <filename>mobicents-all-1_2_0_BETA3.zip</filename> and <filename>mobicents-all-1_2_0_BETA3.zip.sha1.asc</filename>.</para>
						</footnote> which contains a checksum that can be used to verify the integrity of the zip file, and can alert you if the file has been changed since it was uploaded, or if it was corrupted upon download.</para>
					<para>On a Linux system you can use the <command>sha1sum</command> command to verify the integrity of the binary distribution zip file.</para>
					<para>On a Windows system you will need to download a sha1sum-generating program such as the <command>sha1sum.exe</command> program. This will generate a checksum that you can compare with the sum in the sha1 file.</para>
					<para>Note that if the two checksums are not identical, it means that the downloaded zip file was corrupted upon download, or has been changed since it was last uploaded to the server.</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-binary-Mobicents-Installing">
			<title>Installing</title>
			<para>Once the preconditions and requirements have been met, and you have downloaded the Mobicents binary distribution, you are ready to install it. Simply decompress the downloaded archive to a location of your choice, thus completing the install.</para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-binary-Mobicents-Testing">
			<title>Testing</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-binary-Mobicents-Configuring">
			<title>Configuring</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-binary-Mobicents-Running">
			<title>Running</title>
			<para>Once installed, running Mobicents simply consists in changing to the <filename><replaceable>&lt;topmost_mobicents_directory&gt;</replaceable>/server/bin</filename> directory and invoking <command>run.sh</command> (on Linux) or <command>run.bat</command> (on Windows) The precise instructions depend on which platform you are running Mobicents on.</para>
			<variablelist>
				<title>Platform Mobicents is Running On</title>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Linux</term>
					<listitem>
						<orderedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>Change your working directory to the <filename><replaceable>&lt;topmost_mobicents_directory&gt;</replaceable>/server/bin</filename> directory:</para>
								<screen>cd &lt;topmost_mobicents_directory&gt;/server/bin</screen>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>Ensure that the <filename>run.sh</filename> file is executable. If it is not, modify its permissions so that it is:</para>
								<screen>chmod +x run.sh</screen>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>Finally, start the Mobicents Application Server:.</para>
								<screen>./run.sh</screen>
								<note>
									<para>The above command is a shortened version of this equivalent command:</para>
									<screen>./run.sh -c all -b 127.0.0.1</screen>
								</note>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Windows</term>
					<listitem>
						<orderedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>Change your working directory to the <filename><replaceable>&lt;mobicents_folder&gt;</replaceable>\server\bin</filename> folder.</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>Start the Mobicents Application Server:</para>
								<screen>run.bat</screen>
								<note>
									<para>The above command is a shortened version of this equivalent command:</para>
									<screen>run.bat -c all -b 127.0.0.1</screen>
								</note>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-binary-Mobicents-Stopping">
			<title>Stopping</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-binary-Mobicents-Uninstalling">
			<title>Uninstalling</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
	</section>
	
	<section
		id="section-source-Mobicents-Installing_Configuring_and_Running">
		<title>Source Distribution: Installing, Configuring and Running</title>
		<para>The Mobicents source code is also available from the project's Subversion repository; it is possible and often suggested to install the Mobicents Converged Application Server from source. There are several reasons why you might choose to do so:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>to learn more about the Mobicents project's directory structure structure and Maven-based build system;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>for faster access to new features, such as the latest versions of the resource adapters, bundled servers, and examples;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>to access extra documentation included in the source directories; and/or</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>to obtain proper debugging support.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Directions for installing the Mobicents Converged Application Server from source code are available online. However, it is both helpful and advised to first read the following sections:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<xref
						linkend="section-Before_You_Begin_Mobicents_Subversion_Repository_Directory_Structure"/>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<xref
						linkend="section-source-Mobicents-Pre-Install_Requirements_and_Prerequisites"/>
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>After reviewing the sections on the Mobicents directory structure and the pre-install requirements, refer to the online instructions at <ulink
				url="http://groups.google.com/group/mobicents-public/web/quick-start-guide-with-maven-2">Quick Start Guide with Maven 2 and the Mobicents Sources</ulink>.</para>
		
		<section
			id="section-Before_You_Begin_Mobicents_Subversion_Repository_Directory_Structure">
			<title>Before You Begin: Mobicents Subversion Repository Directory Structure</title>
			<para>Before proceeding with the installation, it will prove useful to examine the Mobicents project Subversion directory structure.</para>
			<mediaobject
				id="mediaobj-ss-TrunkTopLevel.png">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata
						align="left"
						fileref="images/top-Installation-ss-TrunkTopLevel.png"
						format="PNG" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			<para>When downloading and building Mobicents from source, we are only concerned with all the files and directories located in and under the <filename>trunk</filename> directory. In the following sections, we will create a local Subversion repository for only the source code and files we need access to, by performing a <command>svn checkout</command> on the Mobicents <filename>trunk</filename> directory. But first, let's examine the contents and structure of <filename>trunk</filename> in more detail.</para>
			<formalpara>
				<title>
					<filename>trunk</filename>
				</title>
				<para>The Mobicents Subversion repository is logically laid out. The top-level <filename>trunk</filename> directory merely contains five subdirectories: <filename>docs</filename>, <filename>parent</filename>, <filename>release</filename>, <filename>server</filename> and <filename>tools</filename>. The <filename>docs</filename> directory contains the source files for this Guide, while additional, supplementary documentation can be located in <filename>README</filename> and other text files in various subdirectories.</para>
			</formalpara>
			<mediaobject
				id="mediaobj-top-Installation-ss-ServersSubDir.png">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata
						align="right"
						fileref="images/top-Installation-ss-ServersSubDir.png"
						format="PNG" />
				</imageobject>
				<caption>
					<para></para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
			<formalpara>
				<title>trunk/servers</title>
				<para>The servers directory contains all of the important files for running the various servers that ship with the Mobicents Converged Application Server, including the Mobicents JAIN SLEE core, the Mobicents Media Server, and the SIP Servlets and SIP Presence Servers.</para>
			</formalpara>
			
			<mediaobject
				id="mediaobj-ss-ServersSubDir.png">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata
						align="left"
						fileref="images/top-Installation-ss-JainSleeSubDir.png"
						format="PNG" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			<formalpara>
				<title>
					<filename>trunk/servers/jain-slee</filename>
				</title>
				<para>The source code for the Mobicents JAIN SLEE server and other Mobicents project servers (currently the SIP Presence Server, SIP Servlets Server, and Mobicents Media Server) lives, naturally, in the <filename>servers</filename> subdirectory of <filename>trunk</filename>.</para>
			</formalpara>
			<para>Because we are currently concerned with installing and working with the Mobicents JAIN SLEE server, it is helpful to take a look in the <filename>servers/jain-slee</filename> directory, which contains a <filename>pom.xml</filename> build file, used for building the JAIN SLEE server, as well as the following subdirectories:</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<filename>core</filename>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>This directory contains the core code, build, JAR and resource files necessary for running the Mobicents JAIN SLEE server.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<filename>examples</filename>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>This directory contains all of the necessary build files for running any of the many examples that the Mobicents Converged Application Server ships with. For information on installing and running specific examples, see <xref
								linkend="chapter-Mobicents_Examples"/>.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>release</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>The <filename>release</filename> directory contains a <filename>readme.txt</filename> file which provides general information on the specific Mobicents release (much of which is contained in this guide), as well as various configuration files.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>resources</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>The <filename>resources</filename> directory contains the code and resource and build files necessary to run all of the many Mobicents resource adatpers. For information on deploying and undeploying resource adapters using the Mobicents Management Console, command line, or by copying and deleting files, see <xref
								linkend="section-Deploying_and_Undeploying_Resource_Adapters"/>. For information about specific resource adapters, see <xref
								linkend="chapter-Resource_Adapters"/>.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>tools</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>The <filename>tools</filename> subdirectory of the <filename>jain-slee</filename> directory contains the resources necessary for running the Mobicents Management Console and command line interface. You probably won't need to worry about this directory.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			<mediaobject
				id="mediaobj-top-Installation-ss-ToolsSubDir.png">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata
						align="right"
						fileref="images/top-Installation-ss-ToolsSubDir.png"
						format="PNG" />
				</imageobject>
				<caption>
					<para></para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
			<formalpara>
				<title>
					<filename>trunk/tools</filename>
				</title>
				<para>A final directory which is interesting for us is the <filename>tools</filename> subdirectory of the top-level <filename>trunk</filename> directory, which contains the source code for the Mobicents Eclipse IDE plugin, SIP Balancer application, and various quality assurance tools (the <filename>QA</filename> directory).</para>
			</formalpara>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-source-Mobicents-Pre-Install_Requirements_and_Prerequisites">
			<title>Pre-Install Requirements and Prerequisites</title>
			<para></para>
			<variablelist
				id="variablelist-source-Mobicents-Hardware_Requirements">
				<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Sufficient Disk Space</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>You must have sufficient disk space in order to install the Mobicents source as well as the JBoss binary distribution. The Mobicents source, once fetched from the development Subversion repository, consumes about 250-300 MB of disk space. In addition to this, the JBoss Application Server binary distribution (version 4.2.2 GA), once decompressed, requires approximately 115 MB, meaning that you should probably have <emphasis>at least</emphasis> 415 MB of free disk space available. Keep in mind also that disk space requirements will change with subsequent updates to the development repository.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Anything Java Itself Will Run On</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Both the Mobicents Converged Application Server and the JBoss Application Server are 100% Java. Mobicents will run on the same hardware that the JBoss Application Server runs on.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			<variablelist
				id="variablelist-source-Mobicents-Software_Prerequisites">
				<title>Software Prerequisites</title>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Java 5 or Higher</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>A working installation of Java 5 or higher is required in order to run Mobicents and the JBoss Application Server.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>A Download Utility</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>A way to download files is required. We will use the wget utility in the subsequent sections, but any common web browser will suffice.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>The Subversion Version Control System or Client</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>The Subversion Version Control System (<acronym>VCS</acronym>) is required in order to check out the latest Mobicents source code. In addition to the command line client, there are a number of other clients that can be downloaded or installed via your package manager:</para>
						<itemizedlist
							id="itemlist-">
							<listitem>
								<formalpara>
									<title>Basic Subversion (the shell client)</title>
									<para>If you are reasonably proficient on the command line, this is the only client you will need. You can get a binary version for your operating system here: <ulink
											url="http://subversion.tigris.org/project_packages.html"/>. Note that I will be using the command line (shell) Subversion client throughout this Guide.</para>
								</formalpara>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<formalpara>
									<title>The Meld Diff, Merge and Graphical VCS Tool</title>
									<para>On Linux and UNIX-based operating systems, Meld is the Swiss Army knife of version control tools (<acronym>VCSes</acronym>). It can do 2- and 3-way diffs between files, diffs between directory hierarchies, and also serves as a graphical <acronym>VCS</acronym> front-end for the Subversion Version Control System, as well as Git, Darcs, Mercurial, Bazaar(-NG), Monotone, Perforce and CVS, among possible others. Note that you also need the basic Subversion shell client installed before Meld can function with it. Meld is available from <ulink
											url="http://meld.sourceforge.net/install.html"/>.</para>
								</formalpara>
								
								<mediaobject
									id="mediaobj-top-Installation-ss-MeldVCS.png">
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata
											align="right"
											width="700"
											fileref="images/top-Installation-ss-MeldVCS.png"
											format="PNG" />
									</imageobject>
									<caption>
										<para>Checking Subversion repository modifications with Meld</para>
									</caption>
								</mediaobject>
							
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<formalpara>
									<title>TortoiseSVN</title>
									<para>A graphical Windows Subversion client which integrates with the Explorer file manager. Available from <ulink
											url="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/"/>.</para>
								</formalpara>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<formalpara>
									<title>Other Subversion Clients</title>
									<para>A full list of Subversion clients is available from <ulink
											url="http://subversion.tigris.org/links.html"/> (look under the <literal>Clients and plugins</literal> subheading).</para>
								</formalpara>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Ant, version 1.7.0 or Higher</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>The Java-based Ant build tool <quote>for tracking, resolving and managing project dependencies.</quote>, which is available here: <ulink
								url="http://ant.apache.org/"/>.</para>
						<note
							id="note-Both_Ant_and_Maven_Are_Required">
							<title>Both Ant and Maven Are Required!</title>
							<para>Both the Ant and Maven build tools are required in order to build the Mobicents Converged Application Server and deploy resource adapters, etc.</para>
						</note>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Maven, version 2.0.9 or Higher</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>The Java-based Maven build and <quote>software project management and comprehension tool</quote>, available here: <ulink
								url="http://maven.apache.org/"/>.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>A Working Installation of JBoss 4.2 or Higher</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Finally, building Mobicents from source requires a working installation of JBoss 4.2. The following section includes instructions on how to download and install the JBoss 4.2.2 binary distribution.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			<!--REMOVE THIS NEXT PARAGRAPH EVENTUALLY-->
			<para>After reviewing the sections on the Mobicents directory structure and the pre-install requirements, refer to the online instructions at <ulink
				url="http://groups.google.com/group/mobicents-public/web/quick-start-guide-with-maven-2">Quick Start Guide with Maven 2 and the Mobicents Sources</ulink>.</para>
		</section>

<!-- the JBoss Application Server Binary Distribution -->
<!--		<section
			id="section-binary-JBoss-Installing_Configuring_and_Running">
			<title>Installing, Configuring and Running the JBoss Application Server Binary Distribution</title>
			<para></para>-->
			<!--<formalpara
				id="formalpara-binary-JBoss-Pre-Install_Requirements_and_Prerequisites">
				<title>Pre-Install Requirements and Prerequisites</title>
				<para></para>
			</formalpara>-->
		<!-- <variablelist
			id="variablelist-binary-JBoss-Hardware_Requirements">
			<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Sufficient Disk Space</term>
				<listitem>
					<para></para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist> -->
		<!-- <variablelist
			id="variablelist-binary-JBoss-Software_Prerequisites">
			<title>Software Prerequisites</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term></term>
				<listitem>
					<para></para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist> -->
			<!--<formalpara
				id="formalpara-binary-JBoss-Downloading">
				<title>Downloading</title>
				<para>First, move to the directory where you want to install JBoss and download the JBoss 4.2.2 <acronym>GA</acronym> (General Availability) binary distribution<footnote
						id="jboss_sourceforge_link"><para>If the given direct link to JBoss 4.2.2 <acronym>GA</acronym> doesn't work for you, the binary JBoss distribution can also be found at <ulink
								url="http://surfnet.dl.sourceforge.net/sourceforge/jboss/"/>, or by searching for the project on <ulink
								url="http://sourceforge.net">Sourceforge.net</ulink>
						</para>
					</footnote>:
								<screen>cd &lt;directory_to_install_jboss_into&gt;
wget http://surfnet.dl.sourceforge.net/sourceforge/jboss/jboss-4.2.2.GA.zip</screen>
				</para>
			</formalpara>
			<formalpara
				id="formalpara-binary-JBoss-Installing">
				<title>Installing</title>
				<para>Assuming you want to install JBoss in the same directory you have downloaded the zip file to, simply decompress it.</para>
			</formalpara>
			<para>For example, the following command will accomplish this on Linux:</para>
			<screen>unzip jboss-4.2.2.GA.zip</screen>-->
	<!-- <formalpara
		id="formalpara-binary-JBoss-Testing">
		<title>Testing</title>
		<para></para>
	</formalpara> -->
			<!--<formalpara
				id="formalpara-binary-JBoss-Configuring">
				<title>Configuring</title>
				<para>Setting the <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> environment variable is all that is required to configure JBoss for Mobicents. The quick-and-easy way to set it for the current session, but which will not last beyond the next reboot, is to <command>export</command> the variable on the command line, and then to <command>echo</command> the variable to make sure that it contains the right directory. For example:</para>
			</formalpara>
			<screen>export JBOSS_HOME=&quot;${PWD}/jboss-4.2.2.GA&quot;
echo $JBOSS_HOME
/home/my_name/jboss/jboss-4.2.2.GA</screen>
			<para>If the <command>echo</command> command doesn't produce any output, make sure that you are in the directory into which you unzipped the JBoss binary distribution zip file, and that the name of that directory is correct in the <command>export</command> command (i.e., that the file name hasn't changed in some subtle way).</para>
			<para>Alternatively, you can set the <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> environment variable permanently in the startup file for your shell. If you are using the Bash shell, this would mean inserting the following line into your <filename>~/.bashrc</filename> startup file (remember to make sure that the path name, i.e. <filename>&lt;unzip_directory&gt;</filename>, is absolute!): <screen>export JBOSS_HOME=&quot;&lt;unzip_directory&gt;/jboss-4.2.2.GA&quot;</screen>
			</para>
			<important
				id="important-You_Must_Set_JBOSS_HOME_If_You_Are_Building_Mobicents_from_Source">
				<title>You Must Set JBOSS_HOME If You Are Building from Source</title>
				<para>The source distribution of Mobicents does not <quote>bundle</quote>, or come with, the JBoss Application Server, so you must remember to install it and set the environment variable. Conversely, the binary Mobicents distribution does come bundled with JBoss; therefore, if you are running Mobicents using the binary distribution, then you should <emphasis>not</emphasis> set <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar>.</para>
			</important>
			<formalpara
				id="formalpara-binary-JBoss-Running">
				<title>Running</title>
				<para>As long as the <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> environment variable has been correctly set, the Mobicents start scripts will start JBoss automatically, as a dependency. Once you have satisfied the pre-installation requirements, obtained the source distribution, and downloaded and built Mobicents from source, then refer to <xref
						linkend="section-source-Mobicents-Running"/>.
				</para>
			</formalpara>
			<formalpara
				id="formalpara-binary-JBoss-Stopping">
				<title>Stopping</title>
				<para>Just as the Mobicents start scripts automatically start the JBoss Application Server, so will they stop it. Refer to <xref
						linkend="section-source-Mobicents-Stopping"/>.</para>
			</formalpara>-->
			<!--<formalpara
				id="formalpara-binary-JBoss-Uninstalling">
				<title>Uninstalling</title>
				<para></para>
			</formalpara>-->
		<!--</section>-->
		
		<!-- Source Distribution -->
		<!--<section
			id="section-source-Mobicents-Obtaining_the_Source_Code">
			<title>Obtaining the Source Code</title>
			<para>Now that that you have successfully installed the JBoss Application Server and set the <envar>JBOSS_HOME</envar> environment variable, we will next download the Mobicents source with Subversion and then build it.</para>
			<para>First, move to a directory where you want to place the files for Mobicents, create a subdirectory named <filename>mobicents</filename> into which you will download everything, and then use Subversion to get the latest version of the sources:</para>
			<screen>cd &lt;directory_to_install_mobicents_source_into&gt;
mkdir mobicents
svn co http://mobicents.googlecode.com/svn/trunk mobicents</screen>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-source-Mobicents-Building">
			<title>Building</title>
			<para>Building Mobicents from source is a simple affair consisting of issuing a <command>mvn install</command> command in the <filename>&lt;mobicents&gt;</filename> directory into which you checked out the sources with Subversion (this directory is named <filename>trunk</filename> in the Google Code Subversion repository):</para>
			<screen>cd &lt;mobicents&gt;
mvn install</screen>
			<para>If the build command succeeds, you will see a <literal>BUILD SUCCESSFUL</literal> message at the end of the terminal output:</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[[INFO] BUILD SUCCESSFUL
[INFO] Total time: 22 seconds
[INFO] Finished at: Wed May 28 13:42:42 CEST 2008
[INFO] Final Memory: 17M/117M]]></programlisting>
			<para>On the other hand, if the build fails, you may choose to:</para>
			<itemizedlist
				id="itemlist-build_fails">
				<listitem>
					<para>Install and use the Mobicents binary distribution for the time being.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Wait a day or so and hope that the build failure is fixed in the Subversion sources. Update your copy of the sources by issuing a <command>svn update</command> command in the <filename>&lt;mobicents&gt;</filename> directory and try to build by invoking the <command>mvn install</command> command again.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Create a new issue on the Google Code issue tracker, located at <ulink
							url="http://code.google.com/p/mobicents/issues/list"/>.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>TBD: Close with a sentence and direct the reader with a ulink to the Running Mobicents (which was installed from source) chapter. Issues that need to be addressed in this chapter include: installing GWT 1.3, which only comes in source for x86 (not version 1.4) and then building the management console.This chapter will have to be expanded with those instructions.</para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-source-Mobicents-Testing">
			<title>Testing</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-source-Mobicents-Configuring">
			<title>Configuring</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-source-Mobicents-Running">
			<title>Running</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-source-Mobicents-Stopping">
			<title>Stopping</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section
			id="section-source-Mobicents-Uninstalling">
			<title>Uninstalling</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>-->
	</section>
</chapter>
