<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter id="pam-Publican_and_Maven">
  <title>Publican and Maven</title>
  <para>The UDS XML is structured in such a way that it can be published using Maven JDocBook and Publican.  Maven, and the JDocBook plugin are used to produce the community branded XML content, and to produce XML that is used by Publican to produce the Red Hat branded product documentation.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Publican Toolchain</title>
    <para>The Publican Toolchain is a set of Linux utilities that work in concert to validate, and publish XML to various output formats.  Publican is used by Red Hat&apos;s  Engineering Content Services division as the de facto standard for producing product documentation according to brand, and translation, requirements.</para>
    <para>For a complete guide to Publican, including installation instructions and commands, visit the <ulink url="https://fedorahosted.org/publican/">Publican home page on fedorapeople.com</ulink>. This page contains, among other information, the User Guide for Publican.  The user guide is compatible with  Version 0.39 and above. </para>
<!--SSDP: Next paragraph is dependent on implementing the Single Source docs project successfully, and the documentation being produced from the one source.-->    <section>
      <title>Banned XML Elements </title>
      <para>For standardization and translation reasons,  Publican  imposes restrictions on what XML elements and attributes are acceptable in product documentation.  Because the Mobicents and JBCP documentation shares a common source of XML, it is critical that the XML source does not contain any illegal elements.</para>
      <para>If Publican is installed on your system, execute <userinput>xmlClean --banned</userinput> in a terminal to view the banned elements.</para>
      <para>If Publican is not available on your system, the list of elements and the reasons why they are banned is explained in <xref linkend="table-fpxe-Forbidden_Publican_XML_Elements"/>.</para>
      <para><table frame="all" pgwide="1" id="table-fpxe-Forbidden_Publican_XML_Elements">
          <title>Forbidden Publican XML Elements</title>
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1">
            <colspec colname="c1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Banned XML Element</entry>
                <entry>Why Can&apos;t I Use It?</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>&lt;caution&gt;</entry>
                <entry>This element is unnecessary. Use &lt;important&gt; or &lt;warning&gt;</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>&lt;entrytbl&gt;</entry>
                <entry>Nested tables break PDF generation. Reconsider your data structure.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>&lt;glossdiv&gt;</entry>
                <entry>This element set imposes English-language order on glossaries, rendering them useless when translated.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>&lt;glosslist&gt;</entry>
                <entry>This element set imposes English-language order on glossaries, rendering them useless when translated.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>&lt;inlinegraphic&gt;</entry>
                <entry>This element breaks Section 508 accessibility standards and makes translation extremely difficult.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>&lt;link&gt;</entry>
                <entry>This element is undesirable. Use &lt;xref&gt; for internal links and &lt;ulink&gt; for external links.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>&lt;olink&gt;</entry>
                <entry>This element is undesirable. Use &lt;xref&gt; for internal links and &lt;ulink&gt; for external links.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>&lt;tip&gt;</entry>
                <entry>This element is unnecessary. Use &lt;note&gt; or &lt;important&gt;.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>
      <para>In additon to the banned elements, there are two attributes that must not be used anywhere within the XML source:</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>endterm</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Hides data from translators and, consequently, causes translation errors.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>xreflabel</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Hides data from translators and, consequently, causes translation errors.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>XML Book Components</title>
    <para>Each book in the UDS is constructed using a standardized structure, to maintain consistency throughout the project.  The structure present as of September 2009 follows the Publican Toolchain directory structure.  <xref linkend="table-Book-Structure"/> describes the mandatory files that must be present, including a description of the file contents, and where the XML file is embedded into the finished user guide. </para>
    <table frame="all" pgwide="1" id="table-Book-Structure">
      <title>Book Components</title>
      <tgroup cols="3" colsep="1">
        <colspec colnum="1" colname="c0" align="left"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" colname="c1" align="left"/>
        <colspec colnum="3" colname="c2" align="left"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="center">XML Book Component</entry>
            <entry align="center">Description</entry>
            <entry>Order of Component in the Book</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <filename><replaceable>[Book_Name]</replaceable>.xml</filename>
            </entry>
            <entry>Contains the structure of the user guide, represented by xi:include references to each chapter-<replaceable>[Chapter_Name]</replaceable>.xml component, and other mandatory components in this table.</entry>
            <entry>Top Level (or Parent) component of any user guide. </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <filename>Book_Info.xml</filename>
            </entry>
            <entry>Contains information about the book title, book version number, abstract and copyright information.</entry>
            <entry>1st Child. This is the opening information a reader will see in the user guide. </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <filename>Author_Group.xml</filename>
            </entry>
            <entry>Contains contact information about the authors that contributed to the content of the book.</entry>
            <entry>2nd Child. This component is included in the <filename>Book_Info.xml</filename> component.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <filename>Preface.xml</filename>
            </entry>
            <entry>Contains pre-defined content explaining the typographical standards used in the guide, and other information that will assist the reader with using the guide.</entry>
            <entry>3rd Child. This component is included after the <filename>Book_Info.xml</filename> content.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <filename>chapter-<replaceable>[Chapter_Name]</replaceable>.xml</filename>
            </entry>
            <entry>Contains XML markup and content included at a Chapter level in the document. The XML file is named only for human-readability.</entry>
            <entry>4th. This is the top level element for each chapter in the user guide. The order of these files in the <filename><replaceable>[Book_Name]</replaceable>.xml</filename> file determines the structure of the guide.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <filename>section-<replaceable>[Section_Name]</replaceable>.xml</filename>
            </entry>
            <entry>Contains XML markup and content included at a Section level in the document. The XML file is named only for human-readability.</entry>
            <entry>5th. This component is included in <filename>chapter-<replaceable>[Chapter_Name]</replaceable>.xml</filename> files by xi:include reference.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <filename>Revision History.xml</filename>
            </entry>
            <entry>Contains a record of the revisions made to the document over time. Top-level information about changes in the guide are provided to the reader.</entry>
            <entry>6th. </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para>To ensure Maven JDocBook can publish the content generated by the Publican Tool chain, additional XML content is required.  Maven JDocBook does not have access to the Publican Tool chain common_content directory. Therefore, the required XML files must be included as xi:fallback references in the <filename>preface.xml</filename> and <filename>book_info.xml</filename> files.  </para>
    <para>The content is contained within XML files in the fallback_content directory of each user guide repository.   The fallback_content directory contains copies of the XML files located in the <filename>/usr/share/publican/Common_Content</filename> directory.</para>
    <note>
      <title>Fallback Content Accuracy Check</title>
      <para>The front-matter information located in the fallback_content directory of each user guide repository, is not maintained by the Publican Tool chain Team, or upgraded when Publican updates are installed.  Therefore, manually verify that the information contained in these files are kept current with the standards present in the latest Publican Tool chain version.</para>
    </note>
    <para>Fallback content is added to each xi:include element that Maven JDocBook does not have access to.  The structure described in the following XML sample is for the <filename>Legal_Notice.xml</filename> information in the <filename>Book_Info.xml</filename> file.</para>
    <programlisting role="XML">&lt;!--FOR PUBLICAN --&gt;
&lt;xi:include xmlns:xi=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude&quot;
 href=&quot;Common_Content/Legal_Notice.xml&quot;&gt;
    &lt;!--FOR JDOCBOOK:--&gt;
    &lt;xi:fallback xmlns:xi=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude&quot;&gt;
        &lt;xi:include href=&quot;fallback_content/Legal_Notice.xml&quot;
         xmlns:xi=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude&quot;&gt;&lt;/xi:include&gt;
    &lt;/xi:fallback&gt;
&lt;/xi:include&gt;</programlisting>
    <para>The xi:include element can have any number of xi:fallback elements defined.  However, in the Mobicents UDS only one fallback is required.</para>
    <table frame="all" pgwide="1" id="table-Maven_JDocBook_Content">
      <title>Maven JDocBook Content</title>
      <tgroup cols="3" colsep="1">
        <colspec colnum="1" colname="c0" align="left"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" colname="c1" align="left"/>
        <colspec colnum="3" colname="c2" align="left"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="center">XML Component</entry>
            <entry align="center">Description</entry>
            <entry>Order of Component in the Book</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <filename>Conventions.xml</filename>
            </entry>
            <entry>Contains typographical standards used within the guide.</entry>
            <entry>Inserted by xi:fallback reference at the end of the <filename>Preface.xml</filename> file.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <filename>Feedback.xml</filename>
            </entry>
            <entry>Contains information about how to raise a bug against the JBCP user documentation.</entry>
            <entry>Inserted by xi:fallback reference at the end of the <filename>Preface.xml</filename> file.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <filename>Legal_Notice.xml</filename>
            </entry>
            <entry>Contains standardized Red Hat legal information. </entry>
            <entry>Inserted by xi:fallback reference at the end of the <filename>Book_Info.xml</filename> file</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Maven &amp; JDocBook</title>
    <para/>
    <section>
      <title>Maven Variables</title>
      <para>Througout the UDS, Maven variables are used to substitute values when Maven builds the documentation.  The values that are substituted into the documentation by Maven include version numbers, installation paths, and product names.  What information is substituted for each variable, largely depends on whether the deliverable is for Mobicents or JBCP.  </para>
      <para><xref linkend="table-SIP_Presence_Service_Maven_Variables"/> lists the Maven variables used within the SIP Presence Service, and explains what each one represents.</para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1" id="table-SIP_Presence_Service_Maven_Variables">
        <title>SIP Presence Service Maven Variables</title>
        <tgroup cols="3" colsep="1">
          <colspec colname="c1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2"/>
          <colspec colname="c3"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Variable Name</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
              <entry>Substituted Values (if applicable)</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>${platform.name}</entry>
              <entry>Substitutes the Platform name, based on whether the documentation is being produced for Mobicents or JBCP.</entry>
              <entry>Mobicents, JBCP</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>${bookid}</entry>
              <entry>Substitutes the Book ID, which is used to populate the book identifier in the preface. The Book ID is necessary for readers to uniquely identify the book when raising documentation tickets. </entry>
              <entry>doc-<replaceable>[book_name]</replaceable>. For example, <literal>doc-SIP_Servlets_Server_User_Guide</literal>.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>${release.integrated.filename}</entry>
              <entry>Substitutes the Binary filename for the release, based on the binary file nomenclature for the community and product.</entry>
              <entry/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>${release.xdms.filename}</entry>
              <entry>Specific to the XML Document Management Server, the binary file name for the release based on the binary file nomenclature for the community and product.</entry>
              <entry/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>${version}</entry>
              <entry>Substitues the product version number for the release. This variable is used to substitute the version numbers in all path names. </entry>
              <entry/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry/>
              <entry/>
              <entry/>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
<!--SSDP: Adding caveat about the early stages of the Single Source Docs not being fully implemented.-->      <note>
        <para>At this stage, not all book have been &quot;Mavenized&quot;.  The Single Source Docs Project is in the early stages, and further testing must be undertaken before the strategy is fully realized.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
