<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]><!-- chapter id nickname: ittsps -->
<chapter
	id="ittsps-Introduction_to_the_SIP_Presence_Service">
	<title>Introduction to the Mobicents SIP Presence Service</title>
	<para>The <application
			condition="mob">Mobicents</application>
		<application
			condition="jbcp">JBCP</application> <application>SIP Presence Service</application> provides presence functionalities to SIP-based networks using standards developed by the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF), the Open Mobile Alliance (OMA), the 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) and the European Telecommunications Standards Institute (ETSI).</para>
	<section
		id="ittsps-Architecture_of_the_SIP_Presence_Service">
		<title>Architecture of the Mobicents SIP Presence Service</title>
		<para>The <application>SIP Presence Service</application> is comprised of three separate but interrelated servers.</para>
		<para>View the <ulink
				url="http://mobicents-public.googlegroups.com/web/MobicentsSipPresenceServerArchitecture.jpg?gda=hTO2O1wAAAAF_VX0TG5xx-FBSRUj3rSwIO4FCNj8IiPb7zdEEjjYwlAgDLzQ8i_XkNckzGVsS4tcrsHvKlAHZlMtp5btUQdlZU3ceRGzPAq0DrjjiW76mv1ab5qObNWgAVSUTtz98C0"><application
					condition="mob">Mobicents Platform</application>
				<application
					condition="jbcp">JBoss Communications Platform</application> SIP Presence Service architecture</ulink>
		</para>
		<!--<mediaobject
			id="ittsps-sps-SIPPresService-dia-SIPPresServiceArchitecture">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata
					align="center"
					fileref="images/sps-SIPPresService-dia-SIPPresServiceArchitecture.jpg"
					format="JPG" />
			</imageobject>
			<caption>
				<para>Functional Diagram of the Mobicents SIP Presence Service</para>
			</caption>
		</mediaobject>-->
		<variablelist
			id="ittsps-The_Three_Servers_Comprising_the_SIP_Presence_Service">
			<title>The Three Servers Comprising the SIP Presence Service</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>The SIP Presence Server</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The <application
							condition="mob">Mobicents</application>
						<application
							condition="jbcp">JBCP</application> SIP Presence Server is an entity that accepts, stores and distributes Presence Information. The <application>SIP Presence Server</application> performs the following functions:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>It manages publications from one or multiple presence source(s) of a certain <emphasis>presentity</emphasis>. This includes refreshing presence information, replacing existing presence information with newly-published information, or removing presence information.</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>It manages subscriptions from watchers to presence information and generates notifications about presence information state changes, retrieving the presence authorization rules from the <application>XDM Server</application>.</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>It manages subscriptions from watcher information subscribers to watcher information and generates notifications about watcher information state changes.</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>The XML Document Management Server</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The <application>XML Document Management Server</application> (<acronym>XDM Server</acronym>) is a functional element of next-generation IP communications networks is responsible for handling the management of user XML documents stored on the network side, such as presence authorization rules, static presence information, contact and group lists (also known as <quote>resource lists</quote>), policy data, and many others.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>The Resource List Server</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The <application>Resource List Server</application> (<acronym>RLS</acronym>) handles subscriptions to presence lists. It creates and manages back-end subscriptions to all resources in the presence list. The list content is retrieved from the <application>XDM Server</application>.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<para>A major advantage of the SIP Presence Service is that, depending on your needs, each server can be deployed separately, or all servers can be integrated on the same host. In addition, there are JAIN SLEE internal client interfaces available for each server, which distinguishes the <application
				condition="mob">Mobicents</application>
			<application
				condition="jbcp">JBCP</application> SIP Presence Service from other presence services.</para>
		<para>For documentation on each server proceed to links under this page Resources section.</para>
		<formalpara>
			<title>Resources and Further Information about the Mobicents Presence Service</title>
			<para>For further information on the Mobicents Presence Service, here is a list of additional resources:</para>
		</formalpara>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Issue tracker</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<ulink
							url="http://mobicents.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/servers/sip-presence/">Source Code Location</ulink>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Forums</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<ulink
							url="http://forums.java.net/jive/category.jspa?categoryID=36">Java.net Forums</ulink>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
</chapter>

